A Guide to the Albert Durant Photography Collection, 20th century
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
- Photoprints. (Box-folder 1:1-14a:16)
  - Churches., 5 folders. (Box-folder 11:1-11:5)
    Includes 5x7 and 8x10 inch black and white prints of African American churches in Williamsburg, Grove, Lightfoot, Grafton, Smithfield, and other communities. These prints record such rituals as baptisms and communion, as well as ministers preaching and interacting with congregations. In addition, they include many group portraits of choirs, usher boards, Sunday school classes, and women's missionary circles. Churches and groups which have been identified include First Baptist Church in Williamsburg, Mt. Pleasant Baptist Church, Mt. Gilead Baptist Church in Grove, New Zion Baptist Church in Lightfoot, Oak Tree Church, St. John's Church, the Shiloh Church Choir, the Lily of the Valley Club, and the Smithfield Church Club.
    - Rev. Banks baptizing at the river and other river baptisms. (Folder 11:1)
    - Sunday School classes, choirs, and other church groups; pastors and laity speaking or performing spirituals. (Box-folder 11:2-11:5)
  - Night Clubs., 5 folders. (Box-folder 12:1-125)
    Consists of 5x7 and 8x10 inch black and white prints of African Amerian night clubs in the Williamsburg area. These prints capture both audiences conversing at tables and performers giving floor shows at such places as Yorkie's Tavern, Aberdeen Garden, and the Hillside Cafe Beer Garden. Since Durant often traveled to other locations to photograph jazz musicians and singers, this series includes a few portraits of such well known jazz performers as Count Basie.
    - Unidentified nightclubs. (Folder 12:1)
    - Yorkie's Tavern, ca. 1950s. (Box-folder 12:2)
    - Performers. (Folder 12:3)
    - Ft. Eustis Band. (Box-folder 12:4)
    - Atomic Swingsters. (Box-folder 12:5)
  - Anheuser-Busch., 1 folder. (Box-folder 13:1)
    Includes 8x10 inch color prints of what appears to be the ground-breaking ceremony for the Anheuser-Busch plant in Williamsburg in 1969.
  - Animals., 1 folder. (Box-folder 13:2)
    Consists of black and white prints of cats and color prints of turkeys.
  - Autos., 1 folder. (Box-folder 13:3)
    Contains black and white photos of individuals posing with their automobiles or driving in parades.
  - Bicentennial at Yorktown., 1 folder. (Box-folder 13:4)
    Includes color snapshots of a Bicentennial celebration at the Yorktown Victory Center in 1976.
  - Hunting and Fishing., 2 folders. (Box-folder 13;5-13:6)
    Includes black and white and color prints of African American men hunting and fishing. Most of the hunting photos are formal portraits of hunting clubs displaying the game they caught. The fishing photos are candid shots of groups engaged in fishing on boats or along rivers.
  - Jamestown., 2 folders. (Box-folder 13:7-13:8)
    Consists of color prints of costumed interpreters and visitors at the reconstructed Jamestown fort and of the monument on Jamestown Island.
  - Log Cabin Beach., 2 folders. (Box-folder 13:9-13:10)
    Includes souvenir portraits of African Americans taken at Log Cabin Beach on the James River. A selection of these portraits are still in their original mattes.
    - Portraits of individuals at Log Cabin Beach in original mattes. (Folder 13:9)
    - Portraits of individuals at Log Cabin Beach. (Box-folder 13:10)
  - Minstrels., 1 folder. (Box-folder 13:11)
    Contains one 8x10 inch black and white photo of performers in a minstrel show.
  - Christmas Cards., 4 folders. (Box-folder 13:12-13:15)
    Consists of black and white Christmas photo cards featuring scenes of Colonial Williamsburg, family portraits, and jazz performers.
    Arranged into broad subject categories.
    - Christmas Cards: Colonial Williamsburg. (Folder 13:12)
    - Christmas Cards: Jazz Performers. (Box-folder 13:13)
    - Christmas Cards: Portraits. (Box-folder 13:14-13:15)
  - S.S. United States., 4 folders. (Box-folder 14:1-14:4)
    Contains 8x10 inch black and white prints of the S.S. United States during a trial run. These photos include portraits of kitchen and wait staff on board the ship, as well as interior and exterior views of the ship.
  - Copy Prints., 16 folders. (Box-folder 14a:1-14a:16)
    Includes 8x10 inch black and white copy prints of photos drawn from various sub-series which were exhibited at the Williamsburg Regional Library in October 1993.
    Arranged by subject.
    - Businesses. (Box-folder 14a:1)
    - Children. (Box-folder 14a:2)
    - Churches. (Box-folder 14a:3)
    - Clubs. (Box-folder 14a:4)
    - Couples. (Box-folder 14a:5)
    - Dances. (Box-folder 14a:6)
    - Death. (Box-folder 14a:7)
    - Family Portraits. (Box-folder 14a:8)
    - Hunting/Fishing. (Box-folder 14a:9)
    - Log Cabin Beach. (Box-folder 14a:10)
    - Nightclubs. (Folder 14a:11)
    - Portraits. (Box-folder 14a:12)
    - School Affairs. (Box-folder 14a:13)
    - S.S. United States. (Box-folder 14a:14)
    - White People: Brick House Tavern Fire. (Box-folder 14a:15)
    - White People: Rockefellers. (Box-folder 14a:16)
- Negatives., 17 boxes. (Box-folder 15-31)
  Consists of 5,188 original negatives and 125+ copy negatives which are individually described in a negative log. Each negative has been assigned a negative number. The copy negatives correspond to the copy prints in Series I, Sub-series 11.
  Arranged in negative number order.
  - DUR 1-344. (Box 15)
  - DUR 345-595. (Box 16)
  - DUR 596-899. (Box 17)
  - DUR 900-1243. (Box 18)
  - DUR 1244-1566. (Box 19)
  - DUR 1567-1869. (Box 20)
  - DUR 1870-2195. (Box 21)
  - DUR 2196-2534. (Box 22)
  - DUR 2535-2889. (Box 23)
  - DUR 2890-3204. (Box 24)
  - DUR 3205-3534. (Box 25)
  - DUR 3535-3862. (Box 26)
  - DUR 3863-4210. (Box 27)
  - DUR 4211-4519. (Box 28)
  - DUR 4520-4829. (Box 29)
  - DUR 4830-5188. (Box 30)
  - DUR 5189-CN - DUR 5359-CN (Box 31)
- Slides., 1 Box. (Box 32)
  Includes color 35mm slides of a wide variety of subjects similar to those featured in the series of photoprints. Of particular interest is a group which documents the filming of "Story of a Patriot" at Colonial Williamsburg. The slides also record a brick-laying ceremony for First Baptist Church in Williamsburg, sports teams and Homecoming celebrations at Bruton Heights School in Williamsburg, distinguished visitors to Williamsburg, and several plantations along the James River.
  - Accidents. (Page 1)
  - Anheuser-Busch groundbreaking. 1969. (Page 2)
  - Business. (Page 3)
  - Children. (Page 4-5)
  - Churches: brick-laying ceremony at 1st Baptist, Williamsburg. (Page 6)
  - Fishing. (Page 7-8)
  - Jamestown. (Page 9-12)
  - Miscellaneous. (Page 13)
  - Monuments. (Page 14)
  - Parades. (Page 15)
  - Portraits. (Page 16)
  - School Affairs: Bruton Heights football team, cheerleaders, homecoming. (Page 17-18)
  - S.S. United States? (Page 19)
  - Viriginia Architecture: Shirley, Westover, and Evelynton Plantations. (Page 20)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Filming of "The Story of a Patriot." (Page 21-22)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Chauffeurs and taxi drivers. (Page 23)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Flowers and gardens. (Page 24)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Historic Area. (Page 25)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Colonial Williamsburg hotels. (Page 26-29)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Merchant's Square. (Page 30)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Colonial Williamsburg staff. (Page 31)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Carter's Grove. (Page 32)
  - Williamsburg Scene: College of William and Mary. (Page 33)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Old Courthouse? (Page 34)
  - Williamsburg Scene: Eastern State Hospital demolition? (Page 35)
  - White People: Rockefeller Family. (Page 36)
  - White People: Distinguished visitors to Williamsburg. (Page 37-38)
  - White People: Tours. (Page 39)
  - Stereographs. (Page 40-41)
    Stereographs of landscapes, a wedding, a church, and a monument.
- Oversize Prints. (Box 33)
  Contains large-format black and white color photoprints of a variety of subjects, including the Queen Mother of England visiting Williamsburg, nightclub performers, a high school band, graduation and wedding portraits, and church groups.
- Personal Papers., 10 folders. (Box-folder 34:1-34:10)
  Consists of correspondence, newsclippings, pamphlets, and memorabilia relating to Durant's career and personal life. Some of the materials in this series were removed from a scrapbook compiled by Durant. Several portraits of Durant are also present.
  Arranged chronologically by format.
  - Church activities, 1949. (Box-folder 34:1)
  - Correspondence, ca. 1970-1981. (Folder 34:2)
  - Limousine business, ca. 1930-ca. 1979. (Box-folder 34:3)
  - News clippings, n.d. (Folder 34:4)
  - Public service, 1975-1976. (Folder 34:5)
  - School memorabilia, ca. 1930-ca. 1949. (Box-folder 34:6)
  - Scrapbook material, ca. 1950-ca. 1989. (Box-folder 34:7)
  - Loose items from scrapbook, ca. 1950-ca. 1989. (Folder 34:8)
  - Portraits of Durant, n.d. (Box-folder 34:9)
  - Negative identification, ca. 1950-ca. 1959. (Box-folder 34:10)